[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you believe it by first recognizing that it will take time for the pressure to subside, especially once you stop giving in to the prior modes of relieving the pressure, such as centrality, distraction, company.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the increase of pressure, because you're not giving in to the old habits of relieving the pressure, you will then have to endure and recognize that it's going to take a while until the mind calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the most important thing is to not give in to those old ways of relieving the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although it can seem worse, it needs to be so before it can get better.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of how these things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, relieving the pressure of household life, once you're not giving in to the distraction, the pressure will start to... well, the pressure can be relieved by sustaining the virtuous behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, initially, when the pressure is all doubled up, so to speak, the... it just might even seem counterintuitive, that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense-restraint and virtue would would relieve this pressure, but actually, if you sustain it, it will, because you're not fueling anymore those habits that have been pressuring even before you started practicing sense-restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the importance there to recognize, is that the pressure that you start with
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the pressure that increases through the sensory strain, it's actually all the pressure of sensuality, all the pressure of desires that you have been giving in to before carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, that pressure has accumulated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have become even more dependent on scratching the itch, on relieving that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you start refraining from that, it's gonna hurt more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that pain is not due to your restraint, as I said many times before.
[SPEAKER_00]: That pain is actually due to the nature of sensuality that's now hitting you harder, because obviously your habits were the ones of avoiding that very nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did not want to deal with it before.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you practice that patience, and purify the virtue, even in the lay setting,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will get to experience that dryness that we spoke about before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dryness from the, you know, these sticky pressuring habits of desires from before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you kind of have a confirmation that the pressure is not lessening in itself, because the nature of centrality remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: What has changed is that your mind now is not perturbed on account of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the pressure that's there, it's not pressuring you,
[SPEAKER_00]: That means, basically, there's no pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no pressure for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see that the pressure now is contained within the nature of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, for example, you would see the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the simile of a poisonous drink, say, the simile of a beautiful beverage that it's actually laced with poison.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you used to drink it, you used to enjoy it, but now you sort of learned that there's poison in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pressure of drinking that tasty beverage, the habit, is still there, but the knowledge of the poison just prevents you from doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still know, you still can remember the taste of it, how enticing it was, but now the knowledge that it will bring you harm is just so established, that you don't even consider it for a second drinking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, although the beverage hasn't changed, the pressure, the taste, the induciveness of lust in it is still there,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have absolutely no desire for it, because the knowledge of the imminent, implicit, inseparable danger from it is apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when that kind of perception is developed, then the sense restraint becomes the basis for pressurelessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: For the absence of that pressure, you now see directly, depending on your virtuous behavior that has been developed beforehand, that has been cultivated, unbroken and sustained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now the mind does not move on account of pressures that are encountered in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not to stop perceiving things in the world that used to cause you pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about not seeing, not experiencing that pressure in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about not being moved by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's even where the practice of samādhi comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about pleasant abiding of thoughtlessness or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It really just comes down to practicing immovability in regard to things that want to move you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust, aversion, desire for distraction and similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with everything that's going on, like in a household setting, in a lay life, you could still
[SPEAKER_00]: Live quite wholesomely, quite skillfully, without needing to compromise the precepts, and recognize that that is the basis for you, correctly and wholesomely, relieving that mind that's been living under the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also an opportunity, basically, to then develop samādhi, in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now as things come your way, one way or the other, there is no more impulsive giving in, overwhelming, giving in to the like...
[SPEAKER_00]: To the pressure that's been overwhelming the mind, you see it come and you see it go away on its own, and any desire to act has been lessened, and obviously, the more you develop this principle, it could even be completely eradicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the true relief from the pressure whereby there is no more desire to act on account of it, desire to get rid of it, desire to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of those desires were rooted in you being moved by the pressure in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, former habits of reliving the pressure must be abandoned, and that lifestyle must be protected and sustained.
[SPEAKER_00]: How it is, where the mind does not move amidst things that used to move it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the pressure is still there, with things that would exert pressure are still there,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, no pressure is felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so that's pretty much some... that's the goal to strive for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to never see or perceive that which pressures you or used to pressure you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simply to not be moved on account of it one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's pretty much a step closer to the true freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...